Finding Aid for University Planner's Office (University of Michigan) records, 1950-1987
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
University Planner's Office (University of Michigan) records 1950-1987
University of Michigan. University Planner's Office.
1 oversize volumes
8 linear feet
9571 Bimu 2
Adjunct of University Architect's Office responsible for campus development and upkeep. Records include correspondence with architects, meeting minutes, reports, photographs and architectural drawings relating to campus planning and renovation; including landscaping, zoning, parking, lighting, walkways and signage.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The University Planner's Office (Donor no. 5582 ) makes periodic additions to the records.
The records are open to research.
The University Planner's Office has historically reported to Plant Extension and is an offshoot of the University Architect's Office. The responsibilities of the two offices have often overlapped and their respective responsibilities for campus development and upkeep are intertwined.
The University Architect's Office was established in 1957 within the Plant Service Department, with Lynn W. Fry the first person to hold the title of University Architect. In 1964 John D. Telfer, formerly the Assistant to the University Architect, became the university's first University Planner. Telfer served in this position until 1968. Frederick W. Mayer then assumed the position and continues to oversee the University Planner's Office to this date.
As stated above, the responsibilities of the University Planner are tangential to those of the University Architect, both being the natural result of an expanding, growing university community. The University Architect's Office devotes the bulk of its time to advising and serving as liaison between architects and the university community on construction and renovation projects. The role of the University Planner's Office is akin to that of a civil engineer and is concerned with the issues that accompany campus development, including zoning, street construction, signage, landscaping, exterior lighting, and parking.
For further information regarding building projects at the University of Michigan, the researcher should also consult the records of the University Architect's Office.
The records of the University Planner's Office consist of eight linear feet of correspondence, memoranda, meeting minutes, reports, architectural drawings, and photographs spanning the years 1950 to 1987. The records document the role of the University Planner's Office in campus planning on the University of Michigan campuses and in conjunction with the City of Ann Arbor. Records include correspondence with architects, meeting minutes, reports, photographs and architectural drawings relating to campus planning and renovation; including landscaping, zoning, parking, lighting, walkways and signage.
The records are arranged alphabetically in one series of Topical Files.
Subjects:
University of Michigan. University Planner's Office.; Construction industry--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Architecture--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; University of Michigan--Buildings.; Landscape architecture.; University of Michigan--Campus.; University of Michigan--Parking.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
University of Michigan. University Planner's Office.; University of Michigan--Buildings.; University of Michigan--Campus.
Genre Terms:
Architectural drawings.; Photographs.
- Topical Files
  The Topical Files (8 linear ft) generally concern issues that arise from the construction of a building or other campus development. These issues are broad-ranging and include parking lots and structures, changes in traffic patterns, exterior lighting, bicycle paths and bicycle racks, recreation areas, signage, pedestrian bridges and walkways, zoning issues, and landscaping. As the University Planner works in close contact with the University Architect, this record group also includes material concerning the numerous building projects on the three university campuses.
  - Ann Arbor, City of
    - General 1966-1981 (Box 1)
    - Ann Arbor Blues Festival 1970-1974 (Box 1)
    - Board of Education (re: Huron High School) 1962-1968 (Box 1)
    - Buffer Ordinance, Landscape and Land Use 1968-1972 (Box 1)
    - Planning Department 1960-1977 (Box 1)
    - Public Hearings on Zoning 1964-1982 (Box 1)
    - R2B District, Zoning of 1969-1974 (Box 1)
      (area of Hill St. and Washtenaw Ave. including fraternities, sororities and cooperative housing)
    - University-City Capital Projects for 1965-1970, 1964 (Box 1)
    - Urban Beautification 1966 (Box 1)
  - Ann Arbor Township 1966, 1974, 1976 (Box 1)
  - Barr, Bradford (correspondence) 1964-1965 (Box 1)
  - Building Program (Ann Arbor Campus)
    - Capital Campaign (potential projects) 1975-1980 (Box 1)
    - Comprehensive Building Program 1960-1970 (Box 1)
    - Physical Plant Development (Box 1)
      (includes copies of historical materials re: campus development dating to 1919)
    - Public Works Projects 1976 (Box 1)
      (includes C.C. Little Bldg, S.T. Dana Bldg, Old Architecture and Design Bldg, University Hospital, Biological Station, Camp Filibert Roth, Engineering Bldg II)
    - Report "The University of Michigan Classroom and Office Building Report on Planning and Development Part I," 1965 (Box 1)
  - Buildings (Ann Arbor Campus)
    - Architectural Research Housing 1966 (Box 1)
    - Architecture and Design Building, Reports
      - "Physical Condition and Reuse Feasibility Study of A & D Building" (Eberle M. Smith Associates) 1976 (Box 1)
      - Report on Planning and Development 1968 (Box 1)
    - Argus Plant No. 2 (includes Michigan Media) 1980-1986 (Box 1)
    - Barbour Waterman Gymnasiums 1950-1977 (Box 1)
    - Center for Research on Human Growth and Development 1966-1967 (Box 1)
    - Child Care Center 1970-1972 (Box 1)
    - Computing Center 1968 (Box 1)
    - Continuation Center Report, untitled 1954 (Volume 1)
    - Economics Building 1971-1982 (Box 1)
    - Engineering Technology Center, Water Resources Educational Facility, Report Preliminary Plan (Swanson Associates), 1972 (Box 1)
    - Fresh Air Camp 1962, 1967 (Box 1)
    - Furstenberg Student Study Center, Report Phase II Report (William Kessler and Associates), 1972 (Box 1)
    - Great Lakes Fishery Laboratory 1980-1983 (Box 1)
    - Highway Safety Research Institute, Reports
      - "A Biomechanical-Biomedical Addition to the Highway Safety Research Institute," 1967 (Box 1)
      - "Outline Specification and Schedule of Finishes" (Harley, Ellington, Cowin and Stirton) 1966 (Box 1)
    - Institute for Social Research, Report, Program Statement (Alden B. Dow Associates) undated (Box 1)
    - Midwest Water Pollution Laboratory and Bureau of Commercial Fisheries 1962-1964 (Box 1)
    - Natural Science Building
      - General 1972-1974 (Box 1)
      - Report, "E.H. Kraus Natural Science Building Survey Evaluation and Recommendations" (Colvin-Robinson Associates) undated (Box 1)
    - University Library, Reports
      - "Conceptual Studies, Renovation of General Library" (Albert Kahn Associates) 1969 (Box 1)
      - Preliminary Planning Documents (Albert Kahn Associates) 1972 (Box 1)
      - "Report for Albert Kahn, Evaluation of Roof Surfaces" (Construction Consultants) 1969 (Box 1)
      - "The University of Michigan Central Campus Library" (Albert Kahn Associates) 1964 (Box 1)
    - West Engineering
      - West Engineering Building, Report, "Historical Survey" (University Planner's Office) 1984 (Box 1)
      - West Engineering Building Survey, (Smith) 1984 (Box 1)
      - West Engineering (Koenig and Williams) undated (Box 1)
    - Wood Science and Technology Laboratory 1963 (Box 1)
  - Committees
    - Bicycle Discussion Group 1979-1982 (Box 2)
    - Campus Planning Staff Committee
      - 1961/62-1972/73, 2 folders (Box 2)
      - 1975/76 (Box 2)
      - 1979/80 (Box 2)
    - Campus Sign Operations Committee 1966-1969 (Box 2)
    - Central Campus Parking Planning Committee 1970 (Box 2)
    - City-University Coordinating Committee (formerly University-City Conference) 1960/61-1977/78, 3 folders (Box 2)
    - Exterior Elements Design Review Committee
      (includes photographs)
      - 1967/68-1969/70 (Box 2)
      - 1973/74-1985/86, 4 folders (Box 2)
    - Exterior Lighting Committee 1982 (Box 2)
    - Housing Committee 1966 (Box 2)
    - Landscape Review Meetings 1964/65-1967/68 (Box 2)
    - North Campus Operating Activities Committee 1966-1973 (Box 2)
    - Northeast Area Planning Review Committee 1966 (Box 2)
    - Northeast Campus Group 1965 (Box 2)
    - Planning Data Steering Committee, University 1966-1970 (Box 3)
    - SACUA Committee on Campus Planning and Development 1961-1966 (Box 3)
    - South Central Campus Group 1965-1967 (Box 3)
  - Dearborn Campus 1958-1974, 3 folders (Box 3)
  - Flint Campus
    - General 1964-1986, 3 folders (Box 3)
    - Reports
      - "Campus Development Plan" (Johnson, Johnson & Roy)
        - Volume One
          - "General Plan," 1973 (Box 3)
          - "Technical Appendix," undated (Box 3)
        - Volume Three: "Plan Evaluation and Phasing Refinement," 1974 (Box 3)
        - Volume Four: "Plan Refinement and Update," 1983 (Box 3)
      - "Court Street Property Study: Land Use Feasibility Analysis," 1981 (Box 3)
      - "Site Investigation, Riverfront Site Proposal, University of Michigan-Flint" (Sasaki Dawson DeMay Associates) 1972 (Box 3)
      - "Specifications for Separate Contracts, Site Construction Work and Site Landscape Work 1981 Campus Site Improvements at the University of Michigan-Flint Riverfront Site" (Johnson, Johnson & Roy), 1981 (Box 3)
      - "Subsoil Investigation and Foundation Feasibility Study, Final Report" (Raymond C. Reese Associates) 1972 (Box 3)
      - "Traffic Impact Study: Riverfront Site, University of Michigan-Flint" (Wilbur Smith and Associates) 1973 (Box 3)
      - "The University of Michigan Flint Campus Plan Study" (Beckett Jackson Raeder Inc.; Samborn, Steketee, Otis and Evans, Inc.) 1971, 2 volumes (Box 3)
  - Fraternities
    - General 1963-1970 (Box 4)
    - Delta Kappa Epsilon 1966, 1968 (Box 4)
    - North Campus (proposed sites) 1961-1969 (Box 4)
    - Nu Sigma Nu 1966-1969 (Box 4)
  - Housing
    - General 1965-1982 (Box 4)
    - Housing Sites 1969-1975 (Box 4)
    - Housing Types
      - Mobile Homes 1966, 1970, 1974 (Box 4)
      - Prefabricated Housing 1969-1970 (Box 4)
    - Inter-Cooperative Council 1965-1969 (Box 4)
    - Married Students
      - General 1968-1973 (Box 4)
      - Northwood IV 1966-1978 (includes photos) (Box 4)
      - Northwood V 1968-1977 (Box 4)
    - Public Housing 1968-1971 (Box 4)
    - Single Students
      - General 1969-1977 (Box 4)
      - Baits, Vera, Houses (formerly Cedar Bend Houses) 1962-1967 (Box 4)
      - Bursley Hall 1964-1967 (Box 4)
    - Reports
      - "Northwoods I, II, & III Planning Study" (Office of the University Landscape Architect) 1985 (Box 4)
      - "Northwood V Specifications, Addendum No. 1" (G. Hellmuth and G. Obata, Architects) 1970 (Box 4)
      - "Program Development for Expansion of Affiliated-Associated Housing Facilities" (University Planner) 1968 (Box 4)
  - Huron River Valley Study/Huron River Recreation Resource Study 1966-1969 (Box 4)
  - Interfaith Center, Inc. 1956-1968 (Box 4)
  - Loading Areas 1968-1969, 1976 (Box 4)
  - Medical Center
    - General 1950-1980, 3 folders (Box 4)
    - Landscape Development 1967-1968 (Box 4)
    - Reports
      - Medical Center
        - "Building Conditions Study" (Eberle M. Smith Associates, Inc.) 1971, 3 volumes (Box 5)
        - "Medical Campus Library & Learning Resource Center, Life Cycle Study" (Hoyem-Basso Associates) 1977 (Box 5)
        - "University of Michigan Medical Center" (Skidmore, Owings & Merrill) 1950 (Box 5)
        - "1980 Projected Traffic Demands of the Medical Center" (Bradford Barr, Engineering Services) 1963 (Box 5)
      - University Hospital
        - "Functional and Space Program" (Coopers & Lybrand) 1978 (3 notebooks) (Box 5)
        - "Interim Renovations of Existing Operating Rooms, Diagnostic Radiology and Clinical Laboratory" (Harley Ellington Pierce Yee Associates) undated, 2 volumes (Box 6)
        - "Progress Report on Development of a Prospectus for the University of Michigan University Hospital" (Coopers & Lybrand) 1978 (Box 6)
        - "Reuse Reassignment Volume: Study of the University of Michigan Main Hospital" (Eberle M. Smith Associates) 1975 (Box 6)
  - Michigamua (re: tomahawk plaque by Tappan Oak) 1969-1970 (Box 6)
  - North Campus
    - General 1964-1978 (Box 6)
    - Schools, Elementary (proposed sites) 1963-1967, 1974 (Box 6)
    - Report, Program Statement, North Campus Commons Expansion (University Planner) 1986 (Box 6)
    - North Campus Report (Aaron Cohen Assoc.) 1986 (Box 6)
  - Pedestrians
    - General 1964-1983 (Box 6)
    - Forest Avenue Pedestrian Bridge 1966-1968 (Box 6)
    - Handicapped 1969-1975 (Box 6)
  - Plant Department
    - Switching Station 1968-1970 (Box 6)
    - Report, "Refuse Derived Fuel Facility for the University of Michigan" (Harley Ellington Pierce Yee Associates) 1982 (Box 6)
  - Recreation Areas
    - Intramural Sports Facilities 1962-1981 (Box 6)
      (includes one b&w negative of 1969 "Intramural Recreation Facilities" blueprint)
    - Northwood I, II & III 1968-1969 (Box 6)
    - Northwood IV 1969-1970 (Box 6)
    - Northwood V 1972-1973 (Box 6)
  - Saint Joseph Mercy Hospital, Old (North Ingalls Building)
    - General 1965-1979 (Box 6)
      (includes 5 b&w contact sheets, 1969)
    - Reports
      - "Preliminary Inventory and Evaluation: Saint Joseph Hospital Property" (University Planner's Office) 1969 (Box 6)
        (includes photographs and slides)
      - "The University of Michigan Building Condition Study for St. Joseph Mercy Hospital" (Eberle M. Smith Associates) 1974 (Box 6)
  - Service Centers
    - General 1962-1969 (Box 6)
    - Report, "CSC North Campus: A Study of Program Development." 1965 (Box 6)
      (re: proposed Commercial and Service Center) (First Year Graduate Students, Dept. of Landscape Architecture)
  - Signs, Interior and Exterior
    - General 1966-1974 (Box 7)
      (includes 11 color photos of exterior campus signs)
    - Medical Center Signage Study
      - General 1978 (Box 7)
      - Report, "Interior Signage Manual, University Hospital" (Smith, Hinchman & Grylls Associates) undated (Box 7)
  - Student Projects 1964-1967 (Box 7)
    (generally re: campus planning or landscape architecture)
  - Traffic, Transportation and Parking
    - Ann Arbor-Ypsilanti Urban Area Transportation Study
      - General 1964-1978 (Box 7)
      - Technical Committee and M-17 Subcommittee 1970-1972 (Box 7)
    - Bicycles and Motorcycles 1964-1970 (Box 7)
    - Bus Service
      - Ann Arbor 1973-1976 (Box 7)
      - Campus 1965-1978 (Box 7)
    - Car Pools 1974 (Box 7)
    - Crisler Arena/University Events Building 1964, 1978 (Box 7)
    - Dearborn Campus 1964-1981 (Box 7)
    - Jefferson Plaza Traffic Analysis 1964 (Box 7)
    - Mass Transportation 1965-1967 (Box 7)
    - Medical Center Area 1957-1987, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - North Campus 1964-1980 (Box 7)
    - Origin and Destination Traffic Survey (North Central Campus and State Street)
      - General 1963-1967 (Box 7)
      - Reports
        - "North Central Campus-State Street Origin and Destination Traffic Survey," 1966 (Box 7)
        - "Technical Supplement," 1966 (Box 7)
    - Parking and Parking Structures
      - General 1963-1981 (Box 7)
      - Catherine Street Structure 1964, 1985 (Box 7)
      - Church Street Structure 1964, 1966, 1971 (Box 7)
      - Compact Cars 1968-1985 (Box 7)
      - Fletcher Street Structure 1958-1976 (Box 7)
      - Forest Street Structure 1976 (Box 7)
      - Hill Street Structure 1964-1969 (Box 7)
      - Parking Meters 1970-1983 (Box 7)
      - Parking Space Data (annual tabulations) 1963-1977 (Box 8)
      - Thayer Street Structure 1964-1965 (Box 8)
      - Thompson Street Structure 1969-1975 (Box 8)
    - Streets and Intersections
      - General 1964-1980 (Box 8)
      - East University Street 1966-1970 (Box 8)
      - East Washington Street Traffic Study (re: impact of Central Campus expansion on Ann Arbor traffic and parking) 1963-1964 (Box 8)
        (includes 6 b&w photos)
      - Fifth Avenue and Division Street 1967 (Box 8)
      - Forest/Observatory/Huron Intersection 1961-1971 (Box 8)
      - Fuller Parkway 1965-1982 (Box 8)
      - Glen/Huron/Fletcher Intersection 1974-1978 (Box 8)
      - Hill Street 1968-1972 (Box 8)
      - North University Street 1963 (Box 8)
      - State Street 1964-1967 (Box 8)
      - Thompson/Monroe/Packard Intersection 1967-1973 (Box 8)
      - Washtenaw/Geddes/Church Intersection 1960-1962, 1977 (Box 8)
      - Washtenaw/Huron Intersection 1974 (Box 8)
    - Student Vehicle Regulations 1959, 1967-1968 (Box 8)
    - Toilet Facilities Survey 1976 (Box 8)
    - Traffic Counting Program 1963-1969 (Box 8)
    - Reports
      - "Proposal to University of Michigan for a Central Campus Parking Study" (Bennett-Ringrose-Wolsfield-Jarvis-Gardner, Inc.) 1988 (Box 8)
      - "A Traffic and Parking Analysis, The Ann Arbor Thoroughfare Plan in Relation to University of Michigan Central Campus Study" (Harland Bartholomew and Associates) 1964 (Box 8)